Inventory to the Charles E. Stuart papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Charles E. Stuart papers
1917-1942
80067
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes, 14 motion picture film reels (9.0 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, memoranda, reports, and clippings relating to the fuel industries in the United States during and after World War I, coal mining in the United States and the Soviet Union, and economic planning; and motion picture film of social conditions and economic activities in the Soviet Union, 1926-1936. Digital copy of motion picture film also available at http://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Stuart, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1881-1943.
Access
Collection open for research.
Use copies of some motion picture film in this collection are available for immediate access; digital copy also available at http://digitalcollections.hoover.org. To view other films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copy of motion picture film also available at http://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
Charles Edward Stuart (1881-1943) was an American engineer who served as chief of the Power Conservation Bureau of the United States Fuel Administration during World War I and as a consultant to the Soviet government from 1926 to 1932.
Scope and Content of Collection
Writings, correspondence, memoranda, reports, and clippings relating to the fuel industries in the United States during and after World War I, coal mining in the United States and the Soviet Union, and economic planning; and motion picture film of social conditions and economic activities in the Soviet Union from 1926 to 1936 titled Soviet Russia Through the Eyes of an American.
The 35mm black and white print with sound motion picture film was preserved through a 1999 grant from the National Film Preservation Foundation.
United States. Fuel Administration.; Coal mines and mining--Soviet Union.; Coal mines and mining--United States.; Economic policy.; Engineering--Soviet Union.; Engineering--United States.; Fuel--United States.; World War, 1914-1918--Economic aspects.; World War, 1914-1918--United States.; Soviet Union--Economic policy--1928-1932.; Engineers.; Soviet Union--Pictorial works.; Motion pictures.
- The Fuel Industry and Planned Economy - United States File (Box 1)
  - Articles and addresses on coal, 1919-1935 (Box-folder 1: 1-F)
    Scope and Contents note
    Ten bound items on coal mine efficiency, coal as affected by anti-trust laws, coal as it relates to the national economy, etc. Includes address on the Export-Import Bank by Charles E. Stuart, as the bank's Executive Vice President, before the American Cotton Shippers Association, April 26, 1935, New Orleans.
  - U.S. Fuel Administration - Various programs, circa 1918-1922 (Box-folder 1: 2-F)
    File containing about a dozen articles on the U.S. Fuel Administration, World War I (Mr. Stuart was Chief of Power and Light Division), including "War Conservation of Power and Light" (June 1918), "Storage Battery Locomotive as Applied to Mine Haulafe" (1922), and "Suggestions to Be Considered in Adopting the Skip-Stop System" (for fuel conservation). Mr. Stuart originated the Skip-Stop System.
  - Black binder (Stuart, James and Cooke) of blueprints of various coal mine design, circa 1915 (Box-folder 1: 3-F)
  - "The Fuel Industry," two typewritten copies of verbatim notes as dictated, 1933 September 14 (Box-folder 1: 4-F)
  - "Coal Hurdles the Anti-Trust Law," Review of Reviews, typescript (3 pages), 1933 March 15 (Box-folder 1: 5-F)
    Also included in folder 1-F.
  - "Marketing and Distribution of Coal from the District of Richmond, Virginia," typewritten report (14 pages) (Box-folder 1: 6-F)
    Includes map of coal shipments throughout Virginia.
  - Typewritten excerpts from letters received by Charles E. Stuart after publication of "A Tested Stabilization Plan" (August 20, 1932) in The Black Diamond, and of a radio talk, "Coal Points the Way to Economic Stability," NBC Network (October 7, 1932) (Box-folder 1: 7-F)
  - "A Planned Future for 120 Million People," by Roscoe C. Edlund and Charles E. Stuart, A Series of Radio Discussions on the National Recovery Act (NRA), #3, for broadcast on station WJZ and NBC Blue Network, August 25, 1933, 7:15 p.m. (Box-folder 1: 8-F)
    Includes an earlier draft with handwritten comments.
  - "A Plan for Establishing an Institute to Advance Planned Economy for Industries" (Box-folder 1: 9-F)
    File of five typewritten papers containing excerpts from an address delivered by Charles E. Stuart on WJZ and a national network on October 7, 1932.
  - "Planning for Industrial Self-Government," typescript (12 pages), 1933 October 5 (Box-folder 1: 10-F)
  - "Planned Economy," address delivered before the Engineers Club of Philadelphia, typescript, 1933 March 28 (Box-folder 1: 11-F)
  - "National Industrial Planning," address delivered before the New York City Rotary Club, typescript (10 pages), 1933 May 11 (Box-folder 1: 12-F)
  - "Central Planning Charts (USA)," typescript (34 pages) and organizational charts, 19?? August 9 (Box-folder 1: 13-F)
  - Comments by Charles E. Stuart following his trip to Europe as a member of the U.S. Government's Commission to investigate the Cooperative Enterprise, typescript (36 pages), with handwritten corrections, 1937 January 23 (Box-folder 1: 14-F)
  - "Objectives of Industrial Planning," by Charles E. Stuart relative to his contribution to a pamphlet entitled The American Way Out, by Howard E. Coffin, early 1930s? (Box-folder 1: 15-F)
  - "The Fundamentals of Industrial Planning Under the Proposed National Recovery Act," address or letter by Charles E. Stuart, typescript (8 pages), early 1930s? (Box-folder 1: 16-F)
  - News release relative to Charles E. Stuart's address before the National Association of Manufacturers' Convention at the Waldorf-Astoria, New York, urging immediate establishment of a federal planning council, typescript (3 pages), undated (Box-folder 1: 17-F)
- Experiences in the USSR During the 1920s and 1930s; The European Economy File (Boxes 1-3)
  - Report of the Firm of Stuart, James and Cooke to the USSR, typescript (circa 70 pages), 1931 May 12 (Box-folder 1: 1-R)
    Describes four years of association between the American engineering firm and the Russian coal industry, and makes recommendations for increasing the efficiency of operations and the productive capacity of this industry. Detailed and very frank.
  - Letter signed by V. L. Piatakoff, Vice-Commissar of the People's Commissariat of Heavy Industry, USSR (copies in Russian and English), 1932 May 27 (Box-folder 1: 2-R)
    Expresses gratitude to the firm of Stuart, James and Cooke for its work in the Soviet Union and especially praising Charles E. Stuart for the manner in which he conducted himself. Attached is a photo of the mine Izvestia, which was constructed according to the design of and with the assistance of Stuart, James and Cooke.
  - Preliminary proposal to Gipromez (for purpose of discussion only) from Stuart, James and Cooke, typescript (9 pages), 1929 March 27 (Box-folder 1: 3-R)
  - Donugol Mine Management Contract between the Russian Donetsky State Coal Trust (Donugol) and Stuart, James and Cooke, two typescript copies (7 pages), 1929 October 8 (Box-folder 1: 4-R)
  - Donugol Report, typescript (circa 55 pages), 1927 April 11 (Box-folder 2: 5-R)
    Letter and report from Stuart, James and Cooke to V. N. Matove, Chief Engineer, Bureau of Projection.
  - Donugol - Report of Technical Council, 1927 May 8 (Box-folder 2: 6-R)
    Handwritten minutes (in English), apparently written by a Russian and signed by the President and Secretary of the Technical Council. Includes typescript Russian translation.
  - Reply of Stuart, James and Cooke to questions of the Donugol Coal Commission, typescript (14 pages), 1929 October 7 (Box-folder 2: 7-R)
    Gives detailed answers to queries relative to procedure, personnel, time cards, vouchers, accounting methods, expenses. Includes a four-page supplement dated November 4, 1929, on details of coal mining.
  - Proposed agreement with the USSR, 1932 (Box-folder 2: 8-R)
    Includes draft agreement and copy of agreement as signed. Apparently establishes a general preliminary agreement between the People's Commissariat of Heavy Industry of the USSR (Narkomkiazprom) and Stuart, James and Cooke. Discusses consultation, reports, travel, technical assistance, possible disputes, and arbitration. Note in pencil says original signed by G. L. Piatakoff, and sent to Stuart, James and Cooke by Amtorg (signed by L. G. Khvostovsky).
  - Agreement Shachtostroy, Kharkov, typescript (18 pages), 1930 December 8 (Box-folder 2: 9-R)
    Copy of agreement between the State Trust for Projecting and Construction of Shafts in the Coal Mining Industry of the USSR (Shachtostroy, Nikolay Mikhailovitch Sagine, manager) and Stuart, James and Cooke. This folder includes another item (Shachtostroy, Cancellation Contract of December 8, 1930), which includes "Diary of Cancellation" and reports, letters and telegrams/cables (in English and in Russian), typescript (48 pages).
  - Copy of Russian reports, typescript (52 pages), 1927 April 11 (Box-folder 2: 10-R)
  - Amtorg - Report on Coal Mining Organization describing for the Russians the organization of coal mining plants in the United States, typescript (28 pages), and three charts, 1932 October 8 (Box-folder 2: 11-R)
  - "Industrial Conditions in Russia," article by Charles E. Stuart, typescript (10 pages), undated (Box-folder 2: 12-R)
    Describes early Soviet industrial development patterned after American methods; mentions first United States firms engaged by the Soviets (Ford Motor Co. for tractors and motors, General Electric (and others) for electrical work, Colonel Hugh Cooper in the development of water power on the Drieper River, Freyn in the steel industry, others); goes into detail of Charles E. Stuart's and Stuart, James and Cooke's work in Russia and their reactions to the Russians and their methods, life in Russia, etc.
  - "Metal Mining in Russia" by Sidney H. Ball, mining geologist, and Bela Low, mining engineer, typescript (41 pages), 1917 March 10 (Box-folder 2: 13-R)
    A review of 1917 status of the metal mining industry in Russia, together with geological descriptions of the various mineral deposits and details of all the principal producing mining companies. States that "Russia stands eighth in the list of world's copper producers, fourth as a gold producer, and first in the production of platinum, and has the most important manganese deposits in the world."
  - "Status of Industrial Management in Russia Today," discussion by Charles E. Stuart before the Industrial Engineers, typescript (15 pages), 1930-1931? October 14 (Box-folder 2: 14-R)
    Very interesting analysis of Russia, the Russian economy and industrial system, the Russian government, and the Russian mind. Includes a draft copy with handwritten corrections.
  - Russia - Parliamentary Debates, House of Commons, London, 1935 February 15 (Box-folder 2: 15-R)
    Copy of report dispatched to the United States Secretary of State, Washington, and routed to officers of the Export-Import Bank (Mr. Stuart was Executive Vice-President of the bank at the time).
  - "National and Industrial Planned Economy," address by Charles E. Stuart before the News Leader Current Events Club, Richmond, Virginia, typescript (14 pages), 1933 April 6 (Box-folder 2: 16-R)
    Review of first weeks of FDR's first term and recommendations for solutions for the United States. Compares U.S. with European economy.
  - "Industry in Russia and the United States," address by Charles E. Stuart before the Thursday Club, New York City, typescript (9 pages), 1933 January 26 (Box-folder 2: 17-R)
    Review of his personal and his firm's work in Russia, frank analysis of the situation in the Soviet Union. Reviews situation in the United States, recommends solutions along lines of planned economy.
  - "Central Planning," address re Russia by Charles E. Stuart, typescript (4 pages), undated (Box-folder 2: 18-R)
  - News Week, Inc., presumably article written by Charles E. Stuart for News Week, typescript (13 pages), 1933 April 14 (Box-folder 2: 19-R)
    Refers to his luncheon with George Bernard Shaw and the latter's reference to and praise of Mr. Stuart in talk on April 11, 1933, and in a personal letter to Mr. Stuart the next day (April 12, 1933).
  - News Week memo to Charles E. Stuart (Box-folder 2: 20-R)
    One half of typewritten questions, presumably sent prior to interview, and preparation of articles in News Week. See also folder 19-R.
  - Time Magazine memo, typescript (3 pages) (Box-folder 2: 21-R)
    Note says that original memo was prepared in May, 1932, "prior to Hitler's incoming," by an editor of Time. Said to have been regarded as a fantastic prediction by the Board of Editors (of the magazine) and, therefore, not published. Memo refers to Charles E. Stuart's opinion re Russia, Japan, and Germany, and his prediction that Italy would go in with Germany and, at the right moment, Germany would attack Russia, etc.
  - File of 91 letters re Charles E. Stuart's radio address of October 7, 1932, entitled "Coal Points the Way to Economic Stability," (Box-folder 2: 2-R)
  - "European Conditions in Their Relationship to International Trade and Export Credits," address by Charles E. Stuart before the National Foreign Trade convention, Houston, typescript (29 pages), 1935 November 15 (Box-folder 2: 23-R)
    Discusses (a) Foreign Trade Policies of England, France, Germany, Italy, Turkey and Russia, (b) Governmental Organization in Relation to Foreign Trade, and (c) Export Credit Aids, Aims and Results.
  - Report on European Conditions in Their Relationship International Trade and Export Credits, by Charles E. Stuart. Section 1 (182 pages), 1935 August 30 (Box-folder 2: 24-R)
    See also folder 23-R.
  - Hard-bound book, same as above (Box-folder 2: 25-R)
  - Russian Planning - Memo concerning statement received from Russia, 1927 December 29 (Box-folder 2: 26-R)
    Miscellaneous documents pertaining to expense accounts, petty cash, disbursement, etc., of firm of Stuart, James and Cooke.
  - Current History, issue containing article by Charles E. Stuart entitled "The Secret of Soviet Power,", 1942 August (Box-folder 2: 27-R)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings re Russia, originating in 1926 (Box-folder 3: 28-R)
    First section about Charles E. Stuart, including his praise of Herbert Hoover's relief work and mining experiences in Russia. Later section contains many articles re Russian trials (especially those regarding coal mining in the Donetz Basin; includes articles telling how a Russian engineer working for Stuart, James and Cooke was accused by the Russians of selling his loyalty to the United States, June 19, 1928). Many articles written by Walter Duranty for the New York Times. Also section on two other American firms engaged by the Soviets, the Freyn Engineering Co. and Colonel Hugh L. Cooper. Then section of general interest re Russia (including one Duranty article entitled "50,000 in Moscow Cheer Afghan King" and New York Times article entitled "Russia Scours World Markets for Cash Wheat: Faces Famine Through Fight of Peasants").
  - Large scrapbook of newspaper clippings, probably starting in 1930 (Box-folder 3: 29-R)
    Hundreds of news articles re all phases of Russia: the military, economy, culture, trials, etc. Much about George Bernard Shaw and Lady Astor's visit to Russia in 1931. Includes a number of articles about Russia-China link and Russia's fear of Japan, as well as about FDR on Russia.
- Miscellaneous - Stuart, James and Cooke Public Relations File (Box 4)
  - Stuart, James and Cooke - history of the firm, its accomplishments and references, and personal résumé, typescript (circa 40 pages) (Box-folder 4: 1-M)
  - Engineering Services - Stuart, James and Cooke, printed pamphlet of scope of activities of the firm and service records of its top personnel (Box-folder 4: 2-M)
  - Miscellaneous public relations - letters, magazine articles, etc. (Box-folder 4: 3-M)
    Includes January 1932 copy of VMI Alumni News (with two-page article about Charles E. Stuart). Most of the material in this file pertains to Mr. Stuart and his firm's activities in coal mining.
  - Clippings re address by Charles E. Stuart (Box-folder 4: 4-M)
    Includes George Bernard Shaw's references to Mr. Stuart's address in New York and subsequent personal letter to Mr. Stuart from Mr. Shaw.
  - Miscellaneous publicity (Box-folder 4: 5-M)
    File includes copy of George Bernard Shaw's letter to Charles E. Stuart, April 12, 1933 (original of Shaw letter is in Mrs. Stuart's safe deposit box); copy of "European Conditions in Relationship to International Trade and Export Credits" by Charles E. Stuart (see also folders 23-R and 24-R); records of Who's Who in America, 1934-1935 edition; letters on European conditions; Industrial Principles Applied to Mining; Report on the Inquiry on Cooperative Enterprise in Europe, 1937; photographs of Charles E. Stuart taken in Sweden when investigating Cooperatives; copies of letters received re Report on Cooperative Enterprise Inquiry; personal letter from Lloyd-George written on receipt of above report; photostat of editorial by Raymond Clapper in the New York World Telegram concerning the possible appointment of Charles E. Stuart as Ambassador to Russia; copies of letters written to the President of the United States (FDR), the Honorable Cordell Hull, and the Honorable R. Walton Moore, pertaining to consideration of Mr. Stuart for the ambassadorial appointment.
- Soviet Russia through the Eyes of an American Motion Picture Film, circa 1926-1930; 35mm black and white print with sound (9 reels), 35mm black and white silent print (5 reels) (Film shelf)
  Access
  Use copies are available for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 80067_f_0007472
  One of the first moving pictures filmed in the Soviet Union by a foreigner, Soviet Russia Through the Eyes of an American was filmed by Charles Edward Stuart, an internationally recognized American mining engineer engaged by the Soviets under their first five-year plan. The film is a travelogue directed by Stuart and narrated by radio personality Norman Brokenshire. Filmed in cities and villages and from trains, river steamers, and bus caravans, the travelogue journeys southward from Moscow to Kharkov and Stalingrad, to the Crimea in the Black Sea, and, finally, eastward through the Caucasus to Tbilisi in Georgia. During the 1930s, the film was shown in commercial theaters in the United States and was used by Stuart in conjunction with lectures to university audiences throughout the country.
  In 1985, R. C. Raack, professor of history and cataloger of historical documentary films at the University of California at Hayward, completed an appraisal of the Stuart film. Believing that the footage was shot between 1926 and 1930, Professor Raack states, in part, "In the documentary film world the footage compiled by Mr. Stuart must be regarded as remarkable because it shows Moscow before the first five-year plan, lively, thriving, almost prosperous. We also have remarkable scenes of Kharkov, perhaps just before 1930, showing some of the remarkable achievements of Soviet architecture before the disasters of complete Stalinization. This city footage and more from Soviet Georgia are the most impressive parts of the material."